<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.6">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-02-02T14:10:11+03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Omar Almoallim</title><entry><title type="html">Concept-Based Image Retrieval</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/category/ir/information%20retrieval/cbir" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Concept-Based Image Retrieval" /><published>2020-10-15T07:00:59+03:00</published><updated>2020-10-15T07:00:59+03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/category/ir/information%20retrieval/cbir</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/category/ir/information%20retrieval/cbir">&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-concept-based-image-retrieval&quot;&gt;What is Concept-Based Image Retrieval?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Concept-Based Image Retrieval (CBIR) allows the retrieval of images based on what is present in the photo rather than the associated tags that come with the photo, including metadata. The need for a CBIR has increasingly become more important as we move towards a more media driven society where camera-enabled phones are practically everywhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to implement a Concept-Based Image Retrieval, the system first and foremost requires to understand images at a high level. This presents two particular problems. Firstly, the intention-gap, a non-technical issue. That is a user intends to search something specific, however it is very broad or has many meanings[1]. A great example of the intention gap iis a user query of ‘ apple’ and in return is presented with Apple Inc. rather than the fruit, or vise-versa (even through an image query). The second problem is the image similarity is very far off the users’ query, this is called the semantic gap. This technical problem is one of the challenging aspects of Content-Based Image Retrieval which are being heavily studied and in this paper 2 models will be discussed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, CBIR allows the retrieval of visual documents using the image itself rather than textual information of the image.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;applications-of-cbir&quot;&gt;Applications of CBIR&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CBIR can be used for various activities. A really important and fascinating one is tattoo image retrieval. Tattoos are becoming more common today with individuals and thus have become a method for human identification. Tattoo pigments are embedded in the skin to a level that become permanent on some level. Over years, tattoos have helped identify criminals[​ 3]​ - even more so when the tattoos have some hidden meaning that becomes easier to identify when there is a dataset of featured images - and also identified victims of different attacks and disasters such as the 2004 Asian tsunami. Another application are individuals who want to find images that are online without the individuals permission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;components-of-cbir&quot;&gt;Components of CBIR&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Query Formation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Query formation is a crucial step in image retrieval as it has a significant impact on the results. The most common query type in CBIR is a query by example (QBE), that is providing an image similar to what the user wants to find. Another query type is by sketch, and more types are shown in the image below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/posts/cbir/queryformation.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Image Representation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Image representation is how images will be compared. When analyzing images, the low-level features, such as the colors, shapes become somewhat useless to use directly for comparison with images as visual objects and scenes undergo various transformations​. Shown below is a way of image extraction, different parts of the image are recognized, then converted into an understandable quantitative description.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/posts/cbir/imagerep.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Image Indexing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is how the images are stored in the database, and specifically how they are organized. This is important as different ways to organize or index can have an impact on how efficient and fast the retrieval is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Concept Based Image Retrieval allows an effective way to access visual data and retrieval of it. A more technical report and details can be found &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/img/posts/cbir/report.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">What is Concept-Based Image Retrieval? Concept-Based Image Retrieval (CBIR) allows the retrieval of images based on what is present in the photo rather than the associated tags that come with the photo, including metadata. The need for a CBIR has increasingly become more important as we move towards a more media driven society where camera-enabled phones are practically everywhere.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Lightweight Cryptography</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/category/cryptography/lwc" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lightweight Cryptography" /><published>2020-09-05T07:00:59+03:00</published><updated>2020-09-05T07:00:59+03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/category/cryptography/lwc</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/category/cryptography/lwc">&lt;h2 id=&quot;cryptography&quot;&gt;Cryptography&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cryptography is one the most important security elements of computer systems and communications today. The idea is to ensure the confidentiality and integrity of information. Cryptography consists of two parts: encryption and decryption. Encryption converts your message/ data into an unreadable text that cannot be understood. Where as decryption is the opposite and converts the encrypted message to make to readable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lightweight-cryptography&quot;&gt;Lightweight Cryptography&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over recent years, technology with constrained resources have become more common and popular in various industries ranging from agriculture to smart cities. The current conventional cryptographic algorithms such as AES were created for servers, desktop computers, machines which are not restricted in resources. Meaning using those algorithms on constrained devises are doable but do not match a desired performance. Thus, lightweight cryptographic algorithms become the solution to secure communications in those constrained devises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2013, National Institute of Standards and Technology (NIST) began an investigation to review if a new standard is required. Two years later in 2015 NIST opened a proposal to process, evaluate and standardize lightweight cryptographic algorithms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proposal’s aim for the algorithms to be:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Block ciphers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Message authentication codes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Authenticated encryption schemes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cryptographic permutations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hash functions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stream ciphers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;post-quantum safe or easily replaced by post-quantum security&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to mention that LWC is not here to replace the current algorithms, but rather introduce something new in the field, as it is crucial that the devices can “speak” the same language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;applications-of-lwc&quot;&gt;Applications of LWC&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two major targets for LWC&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Microcontrollers &lt;br /&gt;
 Microcontrollers are present in almost all modern technology today, whether that would be in a home appliance such as a fridge or a microwave, or in industrial instrumentation devices and process control devices. Unlike computers and workstations today, microcontrollers are dedicated to perform a specific task and execute single applications.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Radio-Frequency Identification (RFID) Tags and Sensor Networks &lt;br /&gt;
 RFID tags have a vast use in industries ranging from farming with animal microchip implants, to the payment systems and supply chain. On the other hand, network sensors applications such as health applications to monitor body temperatures and blood pressures, environmental monitoring of air and water quality, this is particularly important with the research and investments happening with smart cities. Thus, both those devises generally contain significant energy and computation constraints.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned above, the current cryptographic algorithms today such as AES, SHA-2, etc. are made for desktop and server environments where the power and computational constraints are non-existent. That does not mean it is not possible to deploy those conventional algorithms, but rather it has a negative impact of the security performance, thus proving the important need for lightweight cryptographic algorithms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-project&quot;&gt;The project&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two parts that are benchmarked: the lightweight encryption/decryption tested against AES and the lightweight hash functions tested against SHA-256.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Encryption &amp;amp; Decryption algorithms
Four algorithms where tested in total: &lt;a href=&quot;https://csrc.nist.gov/CSRC/media/Projects/Lightweight-Cryptography/documents/round-1/spec-doc/ace-spec.pdf&quot;&gt;ACE&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://csrc.nist.gov/CSRC/media/Projects/lightweight-cryptography/documents/round-2/status-update-sep2020/PHOTON-Beetle_software_update_18Sep2020.pdf&quot;&gt;Photon-Beetle&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://csrc.nist.gov/CSRC/media/Projects/lightweight-cryptography/documents/round-2/status-update-sep2020/Saturnin_update.pdf&quot;&gt;Saturin-Short&lt;/a&gt;, and finally &lt;a href=&quot;https://csrc.nist.gov/CSRC/media/Projects/lightweight-cryptography/documents/round-2/spec-doc-rnd2/pyjamask-spec-round2.pdf&quot;&gt;Pyjamask&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hash algorithms
Three lightweight hash algorithms that are ACE, Photon-Beetle, and Saturnin.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project consisted of taking the four cryptographic algorithms along with the three hash algorithms to benchmark them against AES-128 and SHA-256. The first step was to add a minor modification to allow the API functions (encrypt, decrypt, and hash) to accept external files that vary in sizes from 4kb to 4mb), then add a timer to measure the elapsed time each function takes. However, AES had an extra modification to include an associated data (AD), to make it a fair comparison with the lightweight algorithms. The AD was added by including an HMAC to the AES, then the AES algorithm was incorporated to a similar manner to that of the lightweight algorithm API to allow the same parameters when testing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;results&quot;&gt;Results&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Comparison of all four LWC &amp;amp; AES
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/posts/lwc/encryption.png&quot; alt=&quot;encryption&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pyjamask, Saturnin &amp;amp; AES
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/posts/lwc/enc_pyjama_saturnin_aes.png&quot; alt=&quot;encryption&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Comparison of all three LWC Hashes &amp;amp; SHA-256 
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/posts/lwc/hash.png&quot; alt=&quot;encryption&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Saturnin-Hash &amp;amp; SHA-256
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/posts/lwc/saturnin_sha.png&quot; alt=&quot;encryption&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lightweight cryptographic algorithms are needed to ensure the security of highly constrained devices such as RFIDs, sensor networks, and IoT devises to mention a few. To determine what a lightweight algorithm would be, it should perform faster processing than the conventional algorithms, contain a smaller size code and executable. This report examines four lightweight authenticated encryption with associated data (AEAD) and hash algorithms that are: &lt;a href=&quot;https://csrc.nist.gov/CSRC/media/Projects/Lightweight-Cryptography/documents/round-1/spec-doc/ace-spec.pdf&quot;&gt;ACE&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://csrc.nist.gov/CSRC/media/Projects/lightweight-cryptography/documents/round-2/status-update-sep2020/PHOTON-Beetle_software_update_18Sep2020.pdf&quot;&gt;Photon-Beetle&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://csrc.nist.gov/CSRC/media/Projects/lightweight-cryptography/documents/round-2/status-update-sep2020/Saturnin_update.pdf&quot;&gt;Saturin-Short&lt;/a&gt;, and finally &lt;a href=&quot;https://csrc.nist.gov/CSRC/media/Projects/lightweight-cryptography/documents/round-2/spec-doc-rnd2/pyjamask-spec-round2.pdf&quot;&gt;Pyjamask&lt;/a&gt; that were submitted to NIST completion and succeeded to the second round.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the results show, Pyjamask and Saturnin-Short in fact performed faster than AES by about three times, whereas SHA-256 hash showed much faster than its respective lightweight hash.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Cryptography Cryptography is one the most important security elements of computer systems and communications today. The idea is to ensure the confidentiality and integrity of information. Cryptography consists of two parts: encryption and decryption. Encryption converts your message/ data into an unreadable text that cannot be understood. Where as decryption is the opposite and converts the encrypted message to make to readable.</summary></entry></feed>